Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is י"ז yud-zayin and
we are close to being caught up. We are on ט"ז עמוד
ב', tesh-zayin amud-bet, in the middle of a short דף. daf. And
this is actually quite some very central and important topics that are
about to be coming up and dealing with a major concern of
מסכת יבמות, Masechet Yevamot, which is not ייבום yibum per se, but
issues of personal status in general. And so let's take a look.
And we've already begun this because the גמרא Gemara yesterday introduced the
idea of a testimony from חגי הנביא. Haggai haNavi. Number one, that
צרת הבת tsarat habat is מותרת, muteret, the position of
בית הלל. Beit Hillel. But also number two, that the people living
in these two places, תרמוד Tarmod and
קרדוים, Karduyim, one can accept גרים, geirim, which means that one assumes
that they're non-Jews. As opposed to, apparently, what was a concern, that
they might have been Jews and ממזרים. mamzeirim. And then you could
not accept גרים geirim from them, they wouldn't need גירות, geirus, but
they would still have the problem of ממזרות, mamzeirut, which cannot be
solved. And now the and then the גמרא Gemara had a contradiction
of statements of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan whether you could or could
not accept converts from תרמוד, Tarmod, and that's where we left off.
And now we're going to look at what actually the issues were.
So on ט"ז עמוד ב' tesh-zayin amud-bet we have the following: מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Six lines down, beginning of the line. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
I'm sorry. מתרמוד מאי טעמא לא? MiTarmod mai ta'ama lo? One word
before that. מתרמוד מאי טעמא לא? MiTarmod mai ta'ama lo? Why can
you not accept, for those that say you cannot? Or what's the
potential problem of accepting converts from תרמוד? Tarmod? So רבי יוחנן וסביא.
Rabbi Yochanan veSavya. רבי יוחנן וסביא, Rabbi Yochanan veSavya, a person we
saw yesterday, very rare אמורא, Amora, they debate this. חד אמר משום
עבדי שלמה. Chad amar mishum avdei Shlomo. One says because of the
servants of שלמה Shlomo who were not Jewish, who apparently married women
from תרמוד. Tarmod. Okay, so women who are Jewish women who are
descendant of non-Jews, even non-Jewish servants, should still be Jewish. What's the
issue? Not clear what the issue would be. וחד אמר משום בנות
ירושלים. Vekhad amar mishum benot Yerushalayim. The young women of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
We'll see what that means in the context of what happened after
the חורבן בית המקדש, churban Beis haMikdash, but also again, if they've
got a Jewish mother, what should the problem be? I mean, especially
if we've suggested that the issue is ממזרות. mamzeirut. So not exactly
clear what the issues are. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא למאן דאמר משום עבדי שלמה. Bishlama leman de'amar mishum
avdei Shlomo. It works according to the one who says the problem
is the servants of שלמה. Shlomo. קסבר
עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד ממזר. Kasavar oved kochavim
ve'eved haba al bat Yisrael havlad mamzer. Now this is a pretty
shocking idea to us, right? A non-Jew and a Jewish woman, the
child, well we're all used to saying okay, matrilineal descent, the child
is Jewish, end of story. But actually, here's a position that the
child is a ממזר. mamzer. Or a slave with a Jewish woman,
the child is a ממזר. mamzer. What is this about? So תוספות,
Tosafot, this big תוספות קסבר, Tosafot kasavar, first argues that this is
a function of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position that there is a
ממזר מחייבי לאוין. mamzer mechiyavei lavin. That a child that comes from
an איסור, issur, a
sexual prohibition, even a simple negative command, the child is a ממזר.
mamzer. And that's what it's based on. But then תוספות Tosafot says
one minute, that works for עבד eved because at
least according to a certain פסוק pasuk is read to understand that
there's a negative prohibition to have sex with a slave. But non-Jew,
actually, ironically, although on the one hand it's been seen as the
worst sin, people marry out, they lose their Jewish identity, parents would
sit שבעה shiva and so on. From a technical perspective,
the actual prohibition of sex with a non-Jew might actually only be
rabbinic.
On the other hand, the גמרא Gemara says that if somebody has
sex with a non-Jew in public, קנאין פוגעין בו, kana'in pog'in bo,
like the story of פנחס. Pinchas. But if it's not in public,
and the actual technical prohibition might not be biblical, if it's not
one of the
שבעה עממים, shiva amamim, seven Canaanite nations. So תוספות Tosafot says so
why would the child be a ממזר? mamzer? So one answer he
has is well maybe it's only a ממזר מדרבנן. mamzer miderabbanan. Okay
fine. But then he has another answer which points us to something
not about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and not about the איסור issur
of just a transgression of a לאו. lav. So if you take
a look at the middle of תוספות קסבר, Tosafot kasavar, he says
like this. He
says, ואם תאמר. Ve'im tomar. If you go from the next תוספות
פסול Tosafot pasul and you go up one, two, three, four, five,
five lines. Line starts with the word על בת ישראל הולד ממזר
ועל כרחך רבי עקיבא היא. al bat Yisrael havlad mamzer ve'al karchach
Rabbi Akiva hi. So then it says ואם תאמר, Ve'im tomar, about
a third into that line. People see that?
Yeah? ואם תאמר. Ve'im tomar. Yeah, you see five lines above where
it says פסול. pasul. ואם תאמר *V'im Tomar*, בשלמא *Bishlama* מעבד *Me-eved*
הוי *Havay* ממזר mamzer. *Mamzer* דבעבד איכא לאו *D'be-eved ika lav*, אלא
*Ela* מעובד כוכבים *Me-oved kochavim* מאי *Mai* הוי *Havay* ממזר mamzer. *Mamzer*?
בית דין של שם גזרו *Beis din shel Shem gazru*. That's rabbinic.
ודאורייתא *U-de-oraisa* ביאת היתר היא *bias heter hi*, which again is quite
shocking to us, but then and that's not to downplay at all
the
profound sociological and identity significance of it. But technically if that's true
the child shouldn't be a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*. ויש לומר *V'yesh lomar*
אף על גב דביאת היתר היא מדאורייתא בצינעא *af al gav d'bias
heter hi mi-de-oraisa be-tzina*, as long as it's in private, public is
קנאין פוגעין בו *kanoim pogin bo*. מכל מקום *Mikol makom* כיון דלא
תפסי בה קידושין kiddushin. הוי ממזר mamzer, *keivan d'lo tafsi bah kiddushin
havay mamzer*. כמו בעבד *Kemo be-eved*. That's really not about being a
לאו *lav*, it really is about the fact that קידושין kidushin. *kiddushin*
is not possible. So most of the time when you have איסורי
לאוין *issurei lavin*, מחזיר גרושתו *machzir gerushaso*, יבמה לשוק *yevama lashuk*. So
the one of the major difference between an איסור לאו issur lav,
*issur lav* and an איסור כרת isur kares *issur kares* is that
an איסור issur, לאו *issur lav* even though it's prohibited, if you
do the act of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*, it takes effect. The woman
is actually married. In איסור כרת issur kares *issur kares* she's not.
So what תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* points out is you could have a
situation where there could be no קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* even if it's
not an איסור *issur*. What would be a situation that no קידושין
kiddushin *kiddushin* even though it's not an איסור *issur*? With a non-Jew.
Maybe there's no לאו *lav*, but nevertheless the תורה Torah *Torah* doesn't
recognize the act of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* with a non-Jew. So what
he says is maybe it has nothing to do with רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. Maybe it has nothing to do with a
לאו *lav*. Maybe in certain way it's more similar to the כרת
*kares* idea, not because the weight of the transgression but because there's
no possibility of קידושין *kiddushin*. And that maybe is what this is
is what the identity of a ממזר mamzer *mamzer* is. ממזר mamzer
*Mamzer* is not a child that was produced through a transgression that's
a לאו *lav* or a כרת *kares*. Maybe according to this idea
ממזר mamzer *mamzer* is a child that is produced through a union
in which קידושין *kiddushin* could never take effect. Yes.
Why specifically a Jewish woman and a non-Jewish man?
No, because if it was a non-Jewish woman the child wouldn't be
Jewish. So it would be a moot point.
Although wouldn't the child be able to convert normally? Yeah, yeah. So
does it matter?
From that perspective the answer is yes. Now we're going to get
to that case in a minute so just hold on. Okay.
And then he goes right. Okay.
And fine. So that's basically תוספות's Tosafot *Tosfos's* answer and then he
says maybe it's only מדרבנן *mi-derabbanan*. So we have this radical idea
which we don't פסקן pasken *pasken*. The first part of תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos* we don't פסקן pasken *pasken* this way, thank G-d, right? Because
then because we'd have as opposed to having conversion issues with patrilineal
descent we'd have ממזרות mamzerus *mamzerus* issues. And as was just pointed
out conversion issues are easier than ממזרות mamzerus *mamzerus* issues. Conversion issues
can be solved. So number one is just that we don't פסקן
pasken *pasken* this way. But number two this idea that the child
of a non-Jew and a non-Jewish man and a Jewish woman is
a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*, is it based on a רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* idea that there's a transgression of a לאו *lav* and therefore
it's just a very broad definition of ממזר mamzer. *mamzer* and which
we don't פסקן pasken *pasken* like but again applies to any transgression
of a לאו *lav*? Or is it unique to the idea of
עבד *eved* and non-Jew and has nothing to do with the לאו
*lav*, has to do with the fact that the union is not
קידושין *kiddushin* is not possible in the union which is in the
case of all the איסורי כרת *issurei kares* as well. Okay so
that's a way of understanding this not based on רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* and more similar to the idea of ממזר mamzer *mamzer* from
a prohibition of כרת *kares* because that also is a type of
a marriage which קידושין *kiddushin* is not possible. Yes.
What would a ממזר mamzer דרבנן de-rabbanan, *mamzer derabbanan* be?
Well we'll have that and we'll get to it. Okay. But by
the way I'll give you another example of a child that's a
product of an איסור כרת *issur kares* that isn't a ממזר mamzer
*mamzer*. You know what that is? Child that was נדה *nidda*. Exactly.
So you could have an איסור כרת *issur kares* act of sex
that's איסור כרת *issur kares* that doesn't produce a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*,
נדה *nidda*, because obviously קידושין *kiddushin* is possible in that context and
might even be present in that context. And you could have a
child of a no prohibition altogether that is a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*
according to this opinion which is non-Jew because there's no קידושין *kiddushin*.
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* is pointing us to the idea that ממזר
mamzer *mamzer* might more have to do with the impossibility of קידושין
*kiddushin* than with the actual weight of the transgression. And as I
said luckily we don't פסקן pasken *pasken* this way. We פסקן *pasken*
the child is just simply not Jewish, which allows for,
I'm sorry, the child is no, I'm sorry, Jewish, excuse me, patrilineal
descent I said before conversion, I'm sorry, I was getting mixed up
with the next thing. Patrilineal, I'm sorry, matrilineal descent,
non-Jewish father the child is just simply Jewish. So we don't פסקן
*pasken* this at all and and therefore it is not a problem
but it is fascinating this opinion that it is a ממזר mamzer
*mamzer*. Okay. So that's one approach.
So but what's the story about בנות
ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Bnos Yerushalayim*? So אלא למאן דאמר משום בנות ירושלים Yerushalayim.
מאי היא *Ela le-man de-amar mishum Bnos Yerushalayim mai hi*? What's the
story about בנות ירושלים *Bnos Yerushalayim*? So פליגי בה רב יוסף Rav
Yosef ורבנן *Pligi bah Rav Yosef ve-rabbanan*. It's a debate of רב
Rav יוסף *Rav Yosef* and רבנן *rabbanan*. It's not really much of
a debate as we're going to see. תרווייהו משמיה דרבה בר בר
חנה *Tarveihu mishmeih de-Rabbah bar bar Chana*. And both in the name
of רבה בר בר חנה *Rabbah bar bar Chana*. חד אמר Amar,
תריסר אלפי גברי ושיתא אלפי קשתאי *Chad amar treisar alfei gavrei ve-shisa
alfei kashtai*. One said 12,000 men and 6,000 archers. the destruction of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash whether 12,000 or 18,000.
בשעה שנכנסו עובדי כוכבים להיכל, bish'ah shenichnesu ovdei kochavim la-heichal, when the
non-Jews came into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to destroy it, הכל
נתנו על כסף וזהב, ha-kol nitnu al kesef ve-zahav, everybody else went
to the gold and the silver, והם, ve-heim, and this group of
12,000 or 18,000 men, נתנו על בנות ירושלים, nitnu al benos Yerushalayim,
they went to seize, to rape the young women of ירושלים, שנאמר
נשים בציון עינו, shenne'emar nashim be-Tziyon inu, the women of Jerusalem were,
you know, were oppressed, which actually, you know, is a word that
means were raped, בתולות בערי יהודה. betulot be-arei Yehudah. So basically, it's
the same, I mean, halachically it's the same idea, that this idea
was products of non-Jews and Jewish women. Were the non-Jews עבדי שלמה?
avdei Shlomo? Were the non-Jews the non-Jews that destroyed the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash. that raped these Jewish women? But they were products of
non-Jewish men and Jewish women. And therefore, the question is what is
the status of these people? So according to one opinion, no problem,
right? Non-Jewish man, Jewish woman, the kids are Jewish, no problem. But
according to another approach, which is the one that sees a problem
in תרמוד, Tarmod, the issue is is that no, even with a
Jewish mother, if it's a non-Jewish father, the child is a ממזר.
mamzer Again, we don't פסקן that way, פסקן that the child is
not problematic, okay?
But this is, there is an interesting debate, I should say, by
the way, which comes up, which is whether the child is still
a problem if the child is a girl for a כהן. Kohen.
And that's a big issue. Nobody says it's דאורייתא, de-oraita, maybe it's
not even a דרבנן, but there might be this concept of פגום
לכהונה, pagum le-khunah, and this actually comes up a lot, you know?
Because nowadays there's a lot of cases of mixed marriage, and you
have a Jewish mother, so they say, okay, Jewish mother, kid not
a problem, right? End of story. So we certainly don't פסקן this
גמרא, Gemara, this opinion that it's a ממזר. mamzer, But it's not
end of story because if she wants to marry a כהן, Kohen,
that child, there are some issues that have to be, you know,
looked at. I mean, so there is some debate about that. Okay,
so this is the opinion that the child of a non-Jewish man
and a Jewish mother is a ממזר, mamzer, either like תוספות Tosafot
says because of רבי עקיבא of איסור לאו, or the other opinion
has nothing to do with the איסור, it has to do with
the lack of possibility of קידושין. Either way, we don't rule that
way, we rule that the child is Jewish, no problem. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're going to digress
a little and then come back to this theme. אמר רב שמואל
בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן,
amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani
amar Rabbi Yonatan, פסוק זה, pasuk zeh,
the following פסוק, pasuk, שר העולם אמרו, sar ha-olam amro, the שר
העולם, sar ha-olam, the, I don't know, angel of the world or
the steward of the world said. Now what exactly this refers to,
who is שר העולם sar ha-olam is not clear, but there's a
strong inclination to think that the גמרא Gemara is referring to, it's
not God, as we'll see in a minute, it's מטטרון, Metatron, which
is seen as some heavenly angel that might actually be like God's
right-hand man or some even embodiment of God. Anyway, ask a kabbalist,
I'm just going to read the next lines. You're not at the
level for me to really tell you what's going on here. שנאמר
נער הייתי גם זקנתי, shenne'emar naar hayiti gam zakanti, remember that was
a פסוק pasuk we quoted yesterday, I was a youth and even
grew old. So מאן אמרה, man amrah, who said it? אילימא קודשא
בריך הוא, eillima Kudsha Brich Hu, if God is saying it, מי
איכא זקנה קמיה, mi ika ziknah kameih, God wouldn't say I've grown
old. We might envision God as an old man, you know, but
God would not say of Himself I've grown old. So ואלא דוד
אמרו, ve-elah David amro, so okay, David. No, מי קשיש כולי האי,
mi kashish kulei hai, David wasn't so old that he should say
גם זקנתי. gam zakanti. So אלא שמע מינה, elah shema mina, it
couldn't be God, it couldn't be David, it must be שר העולם
אמרו. sar ha-olam amro. All right. I don't know. Moving on. Okay,
that's really not relevant for us. Let's get to the next line,
which is more connecting to this idea of the raping of the
daughters of ירושלים. ואמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, ve-amar
Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's
meant by the verse, ידו פרש צר על כל מחמדיה, yado paras
tzar al kol machmadeha, the hand of the enemy stretched out over
all of its desirous things, over Jerusalem and the destruction of the
בית המקדש. So who is this צר? tzar?
זה עמון ומואב. zeh Amon u-Moav. בשעה שנכנסו עובדי כוכבים להיכל, bish'ah
shenichnesu ovdei kochavim la-heichal, when the non-Jews entered the temple, הכל נתנו
על כסף וזהב, ha-kol nitnu al kesef ve-zahav, everybody went to gold
and
silver, והם נתנו על ספר תורה, ve-heim nitnu al sefer Torah, they
turned
to the ספר תורה, sefer Torah,
that's מחמדיה, machmadeha, the most desirous thing
is
a ספר תורה. sefer Torah. אמרו, amru, they said, זה שכתוב בו,
zeh she-katuv bo, this... this that it's written by it: לא יבא
עמוני ומואבי בקהל ה', lo yavo Amoni uMoavi b'kehal Hashem, that we
cannot enter into the congregation of God, so עמון ומואב ישרפו באש
Amon uMoav yisorfu ba'eish will be burnt in a fire. Now the
מהרש"א Maharsha points out that the word פרס paras read backwards is
שרף, saraf, and that's part of the play on words that's being
made here. Also though the פסוק pasuk by איכה Eichah also says,
right, אשר צוית לא יבאו בקהלך, asher tzivita lo yavo'u b'kahalecha, the
enemy came into the temple, the enemy that you said shall not
enter into your congregation, that's in the פסוק pasuk in איכה. Eichah.
I found that פסוק, pasuk, yes. All right, should I read it?
Anyway, so that's the דרשה drasha that is being made. Those people
who are not allowed to be part of the קהל, kahal, so
in the simple sense of איכה Eichah it's just saying that they
entered into the temple. These are people that are rejected from the
community and they entered into the temple. But who is it says
they cannot go בקהל ה'? b'kehal Hashem?
It's עמון ומואב. Amon uMoav.
So it's reading, so it's picking up on that hint and reading
that the מחמדיה machmadeha was the ספר תורה Sefer Torah that they
were found that they were being, you know, that was rejecting them
and that's what they attacked and that's what they then burnt. Okay,
and that's ידו פרס צר yado paras tzar and the play of
the word פרס paras and שרף. saraf. All right, so let's just
move on.
I can't find the פסוק pasuk right now. Okay, so moving on.
What?
אשר צוית לא יבאו בקהלך.
asher tzivita lo
yavo'u b'kahalecha.
There you go. Thank you. So the end of the פסוק pasuk
is
אשר צוית לא יבאו בקהלך. asher tzivita lo yavo'u b'kahalecha. All right.
Now, צוה ה' ליעקב סביביו צריו, tzivah Hashem l'Yaakov sevivav tzarav, God
commanded for יעקב Yaakov that the enemies would surround it. אמר רב
כגון הומניא ופום נהרא, Amar Rav kegon Humanya uFum Nahara, like the
city of הומניא Humanya that is nearby פום נהרא. Fum Nahara. And
as רש"י Rashi points out הומניא Humanya was peopled by, populated by
the Greeks, and פום נהרא Fum Nahara by the Jews, and apparently
the Greeks in that city were very oppressive of the Jews. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav Assi, fine.
Back to what we're talking about. So now we've established that there
was this question about this whole place called תרמוד Tarmod and according
to those that it was a problem, it was because the people
there were descendants of Jewish women and non-Jewish men. And if it
was a problem, it was because one would think that the children
would be ממזרים mamzerim of those type of things, which as we
said we do not פוסק, pasken, but it is an idea of
ממזרות mamzerut, as a product not of an איסור כרת but a
product of a union which marriage is not possible. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי עובד כוכבים שקידש
בזמן הזה. Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav Assi oved kochavim shekidesh b'zman
hazeh. Now if that was radical to you, the idea of ממזרות
mamzerus in that context, wait till this, read
this. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי עובד כוכבים שקידש בזמן הזה,
Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav Assi oved kochavim shekidesh b'zman hazeh, a
non-Jew who marries a Jewish woman nowadays, חוששין לקידושין, chosheshin l'kidushin, you
are concerned that it might be a binding קידושין. Why? שמא מעשרת
שבטים הוא, shema m'aseret shevatim hu, maybe this non-Jew is really just
a descendant of the ten tribes, and therefore anybody who's a non-Jew
might be a Jew. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, so therefore maybe he's a
Jew and you have to be
concerned. אטו כל דפריש מרובא פריש, Atu kol d'parish meruba parish, don't
we say anybody who separates, separates from the רוב rov and the
majority of the non-Jews are non-Jews, excuse me, so therefore what's this
crazy concern?
אמר רב בדוכתא דקביעי, Amar Rav b'duchta d'kviei,
we're talking about a place where they are fixed, which means in
a place where we know the ten tribes were exiled. If someone
marries a person who even if everybody there identifies as non-Jews, if
you know that was the place that the ten tribes were exiled
to, then you have to be concerned that the people there still
might be descendant of the ten tribes. דאמר רבי אבא בר כהנא
וינחם בחלח ובחבור, d'amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana vayanaichem b'Chalach u'vChavor,
I think it's וינחם, vayanaichem, this is by סנחריב Sancherev where he
put the ten tribes, where he relocated them to, בחלח ובחבור נהר
גוזן וערי מדי. b'Chalach u'vChavor nehar Gozan v'arei Madai. So what are
these places? So חלח זה חלזון, Chalach zeh Chalazon, וחבור זה חדייב,
v'Chavor zeh Chadyav, top of page יט עמוד א, yod tes amud
aleph, נהר גוזן
זה גינזק וערי מדי זה חמדן.
Nehar Gozan
zeh Ginzak v'arei Madai zeh Chemdan. So now you know. So
if you ever, if a non-Jew from those places ever marries a
Jewish woman, then because that was the location that the ten tribes
were exiled to, you have to be concerned that that person might
actually be descendant of the ten tribes. ואמרי לה v'amri lah and
some say זו ניהר וחברותיה. zu Nehar v'chavroteha. Okay, this is ניהר
Nehar and its surrounding cities. חברותיה מאן? Chavroteha man? So what are
its surrounding cities? אמר שמואל כרך מושכי חידקי ודומקייא. Amar Shmuel kerach
Moshchei Chidkei v'Dumkaya. All right, so now you know. Those are the
places that the non-Jews might be situated. Now, we just stop there
for a minute, we'll say, okay, that didn't say anything, I mean
okay, besides this idea that there still might be descendants from the
ten tribes in those places, it didn't say anything radical about the
idea of personal status. Okay, but now let me ask you a
question, one minute. If they're descendants of the ten tribes, so what
are we assuming in terms of the ways in which they descended?
Are we assuming that those ten tribes men and women all married
amongst themselves and they descended that way, or are we assuming that
maybe they intermarried with non-Jews but we're concerned that these people here
would be descendant from the... If you're concerned that they might be
descendants from the Jewish women of the ten tribes, right, and then
maybe maybe mother mother mother mother keeps on going back and that's
what we're concerned about, so that's what we would say. If you're
concerned that they might be from the ten tribes even in a
possibility of intermarriage, it means you're concerned that somebody's great great great
great grandmother all matrilineal was Jewish, right, reasonable concern, fine. That's what
תוספות Tosafot says or at least one approach of what תוספות Tosafot
says. Now to blow your mind let's read רש"י. Rashi. עשרת שבטים
הוא Measeret Shevatim Hu
about six lines from the bottom on י"ז עמוד ב'. Yud-Zayin Amud
Bet. So רש"י Rashi says שנשאו עובדות כוכבים Shenisu Ovdot Kochavim
that the Jews there, the Jewish men marry non-Jewish women in
these places, so it's Jewish father not Jewish mother. וקסבר דעובדת כוכבים
שילדה מישראל הולד ממזר וחוששין לקידושי ממזר Vekasavar Deovedet Kochavim Sheyalda Mi'yisrael
Havlad Mamzer Vechoshshin Lekiddushei Mamzer
and we're of the opinion here that a child that has a
Jewish father and a non-Jewish mother is Jewish and is a ממזר,
mamzer. patrilineal descent. So רש"י Rashi understands, so wait a minute, I
mean we're going to see the גמרא Gemara is going to continue,
so רש"י Rashi understands that there is an opinion in the גמרא
Gemara that patrilineal descent produces a ממזר mamzer not a non-Jew. Now
if you had to take your choice between, it's not like oh
there's an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that we can go by
patrilineal descent, yes okay so we've solved the whole problem of intermarriage,
no actually if you had to take your choice as we'll see
it's better to be non-Jew and then you can convert as opposed
to ממזר mamzer where you're stuck, but it still is shocking that
there's this possibility of patrilineal descent, that's what רש"י Rashi is reading,
that you're still Jewish. Now תוספות Tosafot is of course shocked. תוספות
Tosafot's says what are you talking about, I mean you know it's
clear that we from all from many משניות Mishnayot not just גמרות
Gemarot that a patrilineal descent is not Jewish, what are you talking
about רש"י? Rashi? So תוספות Tosafot has two answers. One answer of
תוספות Tosafot. is עובדי כוכבים שקידש בזמן הזה. Ovei Kochavim Shekiddesh Bizman
Hazeh.
So תוספות Tosafot has two answers well I'll just tell it to
you then we'll read it inside. Answer number one is that if
you're of the opinion we just said a minute ago that Jewish
mother and not Jewish father makes a ממזר mamzer. because קידושין is
not possible so maybe he says the same would be true in
the mirror image. Meaning if you buy into the idea that that
union creates a ממזר mamzer, so then your basic take is Jew
plus non-Jew is not a question of Jewish or not Jewish it's
fundamentally ממזר. mamzer And maybe if it's true with a non-Jew, a
Jewish
mother, לא קידושין,
Lo Kiddushin, but again it's exact a little funny why that should
work in parallel but he says maybe that's the idea. So if
you said ממזר mamzer. in the case of Jewish mother and not
Jewish father maybe you'll say ממזר mamzer in the reverse. So this
would follow that opinion but since as we said in the case
of Jewish mother and not Jewish father we don't say ממזר mamzer,
we say Jew so then it's not about ממזר mamzer. it's about
identity and then in the reverse we'll say non-Jew. So that's תוספות's
Tosafot first explanation. Yes maybe רש"י Rashi is right maybe that is
what's being assumed here but that's only if you assume, and רש"י
Rashi himself said ממזר, mamzer. it's only if you assume in one
of these mixes that it's ממזר mamzer. then it could be ממזר
mamzer both ways. The other thing תוספות Tosafot says is that no
we're just assuming that they're descendant from Jewish women, non-Jewish fathers, but
it's a matrilineal descent and that's the issue why we're assuming that
they might still be Jewish. So let's just read that in תוספות.
Tosafot עובדי כוכבים שקידש בזמן הזה. Ovei Kochavim Shekiddesh Bizman Hazeh.
So he says פירש בקונטרס דקסבר עובדת כוכבים שילדה מישראל הולד ממזר
וחוששין לקידושי ממזר. Peresh Bakontres Dekasavar Ovedet Kochavim Sheyalda Mi'yisrael Havlad Mamzer
Vechoshshin Lekiddushei Mamzer. ותימא דבכמה משניות מוכח דאין יחוס אלא אחריה
Veti'ma Devekama Mishnayot Muchach De'ein
Yichus Ela Achareha a non-Jewish father a Jewish father non-Jewish mother it
goes by the mother. דתנן לקמן מי שיש לו בן מכל מקום
Detnan Lekaman Mi She'yesh Lo Ben Mikol Makom etc. etc. he goes
through all the proofs. And then he says ונראה דלא קשיא כל
כך Venireh Delo Kasha Kol Kach there's a line starts with the
words דלא קשיא. Delo Kasha. דלא קשיא כל כך דהני משניות סברי
דעובדי כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הולד כשר. Delo Kasha Kol
Kach De'hani Mishnayot Sevar De'ovei Kochavim Veeved Haba Al Bat Yisrael Havlad
Kasher. Okay, והוא הדין איפכא. Vihu Hadin Ipcha. So if you assume
that a Jewish mother non-Jewish father produces a כשר kosher Jew so
in the reverse the child will also be כשר kosher just not
Jewish. Okay and that's the way we do it. רב אסי סבר
כרבי עקיבא דאמר אין קידושין תופסין בחייבי לאוין והולד ממזר Rav Assi
Savar Ke'rabbi Akiva De'amar Ein Kiddushin Tofrin Bechayavei Lavin Vehavlad Mamzer והוא
הדין Vihu Hadin and so if it's true הולד ממזר Havlad Mamzer
with a Jewish mother it's also going to be true הולד ממזר
Havlad Mamzer with a Jewish father and a non-Jewish mother. All right
but it's not
a ממזר mamzer
at
all, no, the כהן
Kohen issue is this. And then in the end תוספות Tosafot just
says that the real answer is this, the easier answer here is
if you look at the word that starts with line starts with
the word יהודה, Yehuda, ונראה דטעמיה דרבי יהודה אמר רב אסי משום
בנות. Venireh Detamei De'rabbi Yehuda Amar Rav Assi Mishum Banot. Okay no
his reason isn't because of Jewish fathers his reason is because of
Jewish mothers. All right so again to repeat because I know I'm
doing this fast and also just give me one second here because
this stupid thing had to be restarted.
Sorry just one second.
Am I talking fast enough today? Okay so... So, so.
We have a גמרא Gemara that says that the people are descendant
come from this city where the ten tribes were moved to, that
exiled to, that they might be Jewish. How would you say they
might be Jewish if there was obviously intermarriage going on? So we
would have said, well, maybe cause great great great great great grandmother
all the way matrilineal was Jewish, you know, and sometimes you have
stories like that. Fine, that's what תוספות Tosafot says at the end,
that that's the way to read the גמרא. Gemara. But the earlier
possibility was no, they actually the reason they might be Jewish is
cause of Jewish fathers and not Jewish mothers. And that's crazy, that's
patrilineal descent. So תוספות says, okay, but if we assume that in
the reverse case of Jewish mother and not Jewish father it's ממזר,
mamzer, which is what we saw earlier, which we don't פסקן like,
then the same would be true in the mirror image that yes,
you would have an idea of patrilineal descent, except the kid would
be a ממזר, mamzer. which is worse than not Jewish because then
there's no solution to that. Okay, so that's what תוספות says is
following רש"י Rashi is one way of reading this גמרא. Gemara. So
now we have two new radical ideas which are interlinked,
which is anytime one parent is not Jewish, the child is a
ממזר. mamzer, Okay, which is crazy, that's not what we're used to
thinking, we don't פסקן that way, but that is what the assumptions
are that are being made here, as opposed to saying no, no
issue of ממזרות, mamzerut, Jewish mother, child is a Jew, no ממזר
mamzer, problem, Jewish father, child is not Jew, also no ממזר problem.
That's what we say. But this approach says any mix, one Jewish
parent and one not Jewish, child is Jewish and a ממזר. Yes.
So we end up saying is right but in the end if
it's a Jewish mother and non-Jewish father the ולד vlad is כשר,
kasher, not even a ממזר, right? That's it.
Correct. Yeah, the only question was פגום לכהונה, pagum l'kehunah, which is
an issue we'll see. Yes.
You got a question? Yes.
If the status of ממזר is like this huge irreparable problem, why
would you ever like look for ways to impose?
It seems like it would... you wouldn't.
It seems like there is
no, they're not looking, they're just saying that that's their הלכה halakhah
position. Okay, so it's not like they're trying, it's just if you
come with that assumption, that's what you have. Okay, so that is
some quite radical idea about what happens with a Jewish father according
to the way רש"י Rashi reads it, a Jewish father and a
non-Jewish mother. So let's continue in the גמרא, Gemara, top of י"ז
עמוד א'. Yud Zayin Amud Aleph. So we have like this. כי
אמריתה Ki amritah
so this was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda reporting in the name of
רב אסי. Rav Assi. Then he says, when I said this over
קמיה דשמואל kamei d'Shmuel in front of שמואל, Shmuel, אמר לי amar
li he said to me, no. בנך הבא מן הישראלית קרוי בנך.
bincha haba min hayisraelit karuy bincha. And now this is what we
are familiar with. This is crazy. If it's your son that comes
from a Jewish woman, he is your son. ואין בנך הבא מן
העובדת כוכבים קרוי בנך אלא בנה, v'ein bincha haba min ha'ovedet kochavim
karuy bincha ella b'nah, but your son that comes from a non-Jewish
woman קרוי בנך karuy bincha that's not your son, אלא בנה, ella
b'nah, her son. Which basically means, hey buddy, matrilineal descent. Okay, so,
which explains right why רש"י Rashi read the earlier גמרא Gemara like
he did, because that's how what this is responding to. So the
earlier גמרא Gemara assumed Jewish father, the kid is Jewish, okay, and
the way רש"י Rashi said it's a ממזר. By the way, the
ממזר point wasn't in the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara was just
could have just been saying Jewish.
And the response is we do not have to be concerned about
the intermarried descendants, about the descendants of the intermarried ten tribes, because
if we're dealing with Jewish fathers, then the kids are are not
Jewish. Okay, yes.
The mishneh Shmuel didn't, weren't Shmuel's daughters kidnapped and raped and had
children by the by the rapists?
Okay, so
that
that would be something appropriate to ask Shmuel.
Oh, I see your point. Oh, interesting. Okay, you're right, I wasn't
thinking about that. That's a good point. Okay, so anyway, so this
is the classic response that in a case of Jewish father, not
Jewish mother, excuse me, yes, in a case of Jewish father where
not Jewish mother, don't go tell me the kids are Jewish, the
kids are not Jewish. Now what does this mean בנך הבא מן
העובדת כוכבים bincha haba min ha'ovedet kochavim etc., what are we sort
of talking, you know, what it seems like he's referring to something.
So I'll just say quickly, I mean there's another גמרא Gemara that
spells this out, but this is it's important. Like we're talking about
matrilineal descent, we might as well tell you what the basic פסוק
pasuk is that we base this whole idea on. Turn this here.
Where's my...
okay, where's my thing here? So the פסוק pasuk is whatever, what
does it say? בתו לא תקח לבנך... bito lo tikach livnecha...
what is it?
בתו לא תקח לבנך... bito lo tikach livnecha... hold on, it's
דברים ז'. Devarim Zayin. לא תתחתן בם, Lo titchaten bam, do
not intermarry with them, right? בתך לא תתן לבנו... bitcha lo titein
livno... בתך לא תתן
לבנו
bitcha lo titen livno
ובתו לא
תקח לבנך.
vito lo
tikach livnecha. ובתו
לא תקח לבנך vito lo tikach livnecha because you see by the
way the way the פסוק pasuk is being written here the daughter
always goes the woman goes where the man is. So don't take
his daughter for your son and your daughter don't give to his
son. The daughter goes with the man. Why? Why should you not
do that?
כי יסיר את בנך
מאחרי.
ki yasir et bincha
me'acharai. Now there's a problem with this פסוק. pasuk. כי יסיר ki
yasir is male. So which man is going to cause your son
to leave me? Right? It could be כי תסיר את בנך מאחרי,
ki tasir et bincha me'acharai, right? The daughter, the non-Jewish women will
take your son away. Or it could be כי יסיר את בתך
מאחרי, ki yasir et bitcha me'acharai, the non-Jewish man will take your
daughter away. But what's the man will take your son away? What
does that mean? So the rabbis say what it means is that
בנך bincha is not your son, בנך bincha is your grandson. Okay.
And therefore the non-Jewish man will take will marry who will marry
the Jewish woman, okay, a Jewish woman, will take your grandson away
from me, but that will be your grandson because he'll be Jewish.
Okay. So if you if you give your daughter which is the
immediate previous פסוק, pasuk, if you give your daughter no, ובתו vito
no I'm sorry, it's not that. It
is actually going back to this. Okay. If if the non-Jewish man
takes your daughter then he will take your grandson your Jewish grandson
away from me. However that is not a problem if your daughter
you give to to their son then you are not I keep
I keep getting the wrong your daughter their daughter you take your
son takes their daughter marries a non-Jewish woman then there's no concern
of leading your your grandson astray because your grandson isn't Jewish to
begin with. So based on the כי יסיר ki yasir what does
this mean? The male will take your male son away. We read
that as when a non-Jewish man is with a Jewish woman then
the then the child is Jewish and the non-Jewish father will take
your grandson away and that's what the פסוק pasuk means here just
to read how that's implicit here back to the גמרא. Gemara. So
back to the גמרא Gemara it says right? בנך הבא מן הישראלית
קרוי בנך, bincha haba min hayisraelit kari bincha, your son that meaning
your grandson right? That comes from the Jewish woman with the non-Jewish
man, that's your son that's Jewish. ואין בנך הבא מן העובדת כוכבים
ve'ein bincha haba min
ha'ovedet kochavim
but a child from a non-Jewish woman and a Jewish man that's
not קרוי בנך אלא בנו kari bincha ela bno and therefore the
תורה Torah is not concerned that the non-Jewish mother will take your
grandson away because it won't be your grandson it won't be Jewish.
He won't be Jewish. Yeah.
That passage is specifically referring to the seven nations of כנען. Canaan.
Right. So there's a question whether it's referring to דווקא davka the
seven nations or all non-Jews but it's still understood whatever it's prohibiting
that it's framing the assumption of whose of Jewish identity. So this
פסוק pasuk is the פסוק pasuk that they hinge this idea on
that it goes by matrilineal descent. Okay that's a lot to hinge
on a יוד. yud. But that's what they hinged it on. Alright.
Now instead of matrilineal descent? Yeah.
It is the the father the the the מחותן mechutan as it
were is the is the male. Right and in that case it's
opposite.
Right and he'll take your son away because of זרה. zara. Right.
So תוספות deals a place with some of those possibilities. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבינא ve'amar Ravina ויקח בנות. vayeeka banot.
So the גמרא Gemara says okay that's all very nice but some
of those people might be descendant from so it's very nice that
we say oh we don't have to worry about about you know
ten tribes because all the kids from the non-Jewish mothers are not
Jewish. But what about the Jewish mothers who were part of the
ten tribes? Maybe some of the kids are descendant from Jewish mothers?
So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר ואמר רבינא ve'amar Ravina שמע מינה
shema mina בן בתך הבא מן עובד כוכבים ben bitcha haba min
oved kochavim קרוי בנך. kari bincha. And we know so if they're
descendant from Jewish mothers and with non-Jewish husbands Ravina says that I
mean this is pretty implicit from the previous statement that that the
son of your daughter בן בתך הבא מן עובד כוכבים ben bitcha
haba min oved kochavim meaning who your the son of your daughter
who had sex with a non-Jewish man so the case of a
Jewish mother and a non-Jewish father קרוי בנך kari bincha is your
son. Okay so so very nice we go by only matrilineal descent
not patrilineal descent and therefore we don't have to be concerned that
these descendants of the ten tribes might be Jewish because the fathers
who cares that the fathers were Jewish the mothers weren't. It says
well but maybe the mothers were Jewish right? Maybe their maternal
great great great grandmother... So the גמרא Gemara says no, גמירי, gemiri,
we have a tradition דבנשי דההוא דרא, debanshei de-hahu dara, the women
of that generation of the ten tribes that were exiled, איצטרויי איצטרו.
itztaruy itztaru. They
were—רש"י Rashi says it means basically their wombs were—were somehow burst. Somehow
they were infertile. Okay, so we have a tradition that nobody came
out of the Jewish women of the ten tribes. Any descendants of
the ten tribes are only from Jewish men, okay, which is quite
interesting because some people in their sort of like eschatological visions that
the ten tribes get restored and so on according to this, it’s
not possible for the ten tribes to get restored. There’s no descendants
of the Jewish women from the ten tribes; they’re only descendants of
the Jewish men. What?
They all convert? What?
Is every—is that listed
or no, that—yeah, I mean, I... I don't know what that means,
yeah.
Didn't the רב—didn't רב עובדיה יוסף Rav Ovadia Yosef rule that the
אתיופים Ethiopians were שבט דן? Shevet Dan?
Yeah, so I don't know. Maybe, maybe here he read the גמרא
Gemara דוקא davka about, you know, as a general statement. I'm not
sure. But it's a good point. Right, you deal with—there are these
discussions about the אתיופים Ethiopians and descendants of—true. So, איכא דאמרי, Ika
d'amri, some say, כי אמריתה קמיה דשמואל אמר לי לא זזו משם
עד שעשאום עובדי כוכבים גמורים. Ki amritah kamei de-Shmuel amar li lo
zazu misham ad she-asa'um ovdei kochavim gemurim. That some say when I
told this to שמואל, Shmuel, that there’s an opinion that says that
the people in those places might be descendants from the ten tribes,
then שמואל Shmuel said, "No, they did not move from there until
they were—until they made them complete as non-Jews." So who’s the "they"
who made them as non-Jews? Does it mean there was a הלכה
halakhic ruling that they were non-Jews for the reason we said before
because they were all descendants from non-Jewish mothers? Not clear. But now
we're going to see a פסוק, pasuk, שנאמר, shenemar, as the פסוק
pasuk says, בה' בגדו כי בנים זרים ילדו. Ba-Hashem bagadu ki banim
zarim yaladu. They rejected God; they gave birth to non-Jewish children or
to foreign children. So does that mean that they had assimilated so
much that they lost their Jewish identity? Right? That would be one
way of reading it, which would also be pretty radical, but there
are those who have suggested reading it that way. Or is this
just another way of saying what we said before? The kids were
not Jewish. Why were the kids not Jewish? Because it was all
Jewish men with non-Jewish women. And since all of the kids were
not Jewish, it wasn't descendants of the Jewish mothers, just descendants of
Jewish fathers. Therefore, it was acknowledged that all of the people in
the places where the ten tribes were exiled were all non-Jews because
none of them had a Jewish, you know, maternal Jewish grandmother. They
all were descendants only from Jewish fathers, not from Jewish mothers. So
we said some pretty darn radical things in these last few lines.
First, just to recap what we said: we said that according to
one approach, a non-Jewish father and Jewish mother, the child is a
ממזר, even though it’s not איסור כרת or anything, but because קידושין
לא תופסין. kiddushin lo tofsin. We obviously don’t פוסקין paskin that way;
at most it’s a question for כהונה. kehunah. And we’ve also said,
according to the way רש"י Rashi read an earlier גמרא, Gemara, that
the flip is also true.
A Jewish father and non-Jewish mother, the child's also a ממזר. Not
not-Jewish; the child's a ממזר. So תוספות of course says that can't
be possible. It’s clearly not the way we פוסקין paskin all these
other משניות. mishnayot. At most, it’s only within the idea of ממזר.
If you say ממזר in one direction, you say ממזר in the
other direction. Okay, but it is still shocking that there's a possible
read that even acknowledging that the child's a ממזר, that there's an
element of patrilineal descent. That then has been rejected now on יז
עמוד א, Yud Zayin Amud Aleph, where the גמרא Gemara completely said,
"Absolutely not, any descendant of a non-Jewish mother, the child is not
Jewish," and the only way you have a descendant that is Jewish
is if Jewish mother, you know, matrilineal all the way up, and
giving the פסוק, pasuk, כי יסיר את בנך, Ki yasir et bincha,
as the basis for that idea that it's all matrilineal. Again, that's
completely assumed by all the תנאי Tannaitic material, with or without the
פסוק, pasuk, that it's all matrilineal. And nevertheless, you don't have to
worry about the people in this place of the ten tribes because
maybe they have a matrilineal descent? No, we have a tradition that
the Jewish women were all infertile, and therefore any descendants are only
from Jewish men, not from Jewish women. And therefore they're all not-Jews.
So according to this גמרא, Gemara, there's no Jews from the ten
tribes that are left. Yes.
That last verse from הושע, Hoshea, the context seems to be he's
prophesying before the destruction of the first Temple that everybody was intermarrying.
Oh, that's interesting. Okay. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: יתיב רב יוסף אחורי דרב כהנא. Yativ Rav Yosef achorei
de-Rav Kahana. All right, so that was pretty heavy. Now we get
to a little bit lighter. But again, that's a very compressed few
lines about Jewish identity that we just read. יתיב רב יוסף אחורי
דרב כהנא ויתיב רב כהנא קמיה דרב יהודה. Yativ Rav Yosef achorei
de-Rav Kahana ve-yativ Rav Kahana kamei de-Rav Yehuda. רב יוסף sat behind
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, and רב כהנא Rav Kahana was in the
front row of the class and he was sitting in front of
רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. ויתיב וקאמר, Ve-yativ ve-ka'amar, and רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda was sitting and saying: עתידין ישראל דעבדי יומא טבא כי חרבי
תרמוד. Atidin Yisrael de-avdi yoma tava ki charvi Tarmod. The Jews will
make a holiday if תרמוד Tarmod is destroyed. Why? Because we just
learned before that there's some opinions that the people of תרמוד Tarmod
might be ממזרים; mamzerim; there’s a question of are they ממזרים mamzerim
or are they non-Jews? And רש"י Rashi says that according to the
idea that they were ממזרים, mamzerim, so since there was... like a
lot of presumably intermarriage with them or other it was it was
very it was very problematic that again whether non-Jews or ממזרים mamzerim
why people intermarrying, but that's the reality that there was that they
were sort of seeping into the Jewish community, so it'll be good
when that's destroyed. I don't know that the people would be destroyed,
let's say nice so the people will be dispersed. Okay, anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says כי חרבי תמוד. ki charvi Tamod. סו הכא
חריף, So hacha charif, so what what are you bothered with? It
is already destroyed. No, ההיא תמוד הוה. hahi Tamod hava. No, no,
no, the city that was destroyed is תמוד, Tamod, not תרמוד. Tarmod.
והא אמרי היינו תרמוד היינו תמוד, Ve-ha amri hainu Tarmod hainu Tamod,
no no, the same city, but איכפולי הוא דמיכפל, ichpuli hu de-michpal,
it like redoubled, meaning like it got rebuilt after it was destroyed.
חריב מהאי גיסא, Chariv me-hai gisa, if one side of the city
is destroyed, יסוב מהאי גיסא, yisov me-hai gisa, then then it gets
built up on the other half. ואי חריב מהאי גיסא, Ve-i chariv
me-hai gisa, and if that half is destroyed, then ותי מהאי גיסא,
u-si me-hai gisa, it gets built up in the first half. So
anyway, this is like a persistent it sort of like the גמרא
Gemara of the תורה צנים וצידיכם, tzinim u-tzideichem, it's a persistent city
that doesn't go away, that the people there are ממזרים mamzerim and
constantly creates problems for the Jewish community. And this as I said,
what we're learning in this דף, daf, we've completely departed from discussions
of יבום, yibum, but is a major focus of מסכת יבמות, Masechet
Yevamot, the issue of ממזרים mamzerim and Jewish identity and marrying and
who's marrying whom and so on. So this is a little bit
of a precursor of very central themes that we'll be seeing. What?
Harsh, right?
Yeah, they should be dead?
Well
that's why I reframed it as the city should be destroyed and
people should be dispersed. Okay, that was my reframing. יתיב רב המנונא
קמיה דעולא, Yasiv Rav Hamnuna kamei de-Ulla, רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was
sitting in front of עולא. Ulla. וגאוי בשמעתתא, Ve-gahavei be-shma'atsa, and he
was having a challenge, and עולא Ulla was sort of like asking
him challenging questions in the learning. אמר, so רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
said, מה גברא, ma gavra, what a great person this is, he
asks such good questions. ומה גברא אילאו דהרפניא מעשה, U-ma gavra i-lav
de-Harfanya ma'aseh, and imagine how great this person would be if his
city wasn't הרפניא, Harfanya, if he didn't come from a questionable descent.
Apparently הרפניא Harfanya was a city like תרמוד Tarmod that there was
not ממזרות mamzerut but questions about the יוחסין yuchsin of that city.
So he said, oh my gosh, this guy's such a big such
an important person, too bad that he's from הרפניא, Harfanya, that's sort
of pulling him down.
So
the
גמרא Gemara said איכסיף, ichsif, he
was embarrassed. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so עולא Ulla said to him,
כסף גולגולתא, kesef gulgulta, little play, איכסיף ichsif and כסף. kesef. כסף
גולגולתא להיכא יהבת, Kesef gulgulta le-heika yahavas, where do you pay your
poll tax to?
אמר ליה לפום נהרה. Amar lei le-Pum Nahara. He says, oh, I
pay it to the city of פום נהרה. Pum Nahara. So presumably
that meant that that's, even if you're like a New York resident
or US resident living somewhere else, you still have to pay some
of your taxes back to the US or to New York or
whatever. So apparently he was living רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna was living
in הרפניא, Harfanya, but he paid his taxes to פום נהרה. Pum
Nahara. And you might remember before we mentioned פום נהרה Pum Nahara
as a Jewish city. So he said אמר ליה, amar lei, oh,
אם כן מפום נהרה את. im ken mi-Pum Nahara at. Oh, okay,
so you really come from פום נהרה, Pum Nahara, you might have
been living in הרפניא, Harfanya, so don't worry, you have an okay
descent. All right, מאי הרפניא, mai Harfanya, what is this הרפניא? Harfanya?
אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, הר שכל פונים בו. har she-kol
ponim bo. Now why is it seen as such a problematic place
and we're going to do a little דרש drash on the word:
הר שכל פונים בו, har she-kol ponim bo, it's a city that
everybody turns to, meaning everybody all the פסולים psulim go to it.
Anybody with questionable parentage, they all go to this city of הרפניא,
Harfanya, nobody else wants to marry with them. במתניתא תנא, Be-matnisa tana,
in a ברייתא Beraisa we taught: כל שאין מכיר משפחתו ושבטו נפנה
לשם. kol she-ein makir mishpachto ve-shivto nifneh le-sham. Again, anybody with some
questionable parentage goes to that city, other people don't want to marry
if you don't know what your יחוס yichus is. So here again
we see even outside of the question of ממזרים, mamzerim, nobody's saying
ממזרים, mamzerim, just לא מכיר משפחתו ושבטו, lo makir mishpachto ve-shivto, nevertheless
the high focus on יחוס yichus and knowing exactly where you come
from and who your parents were was a heightened level of concern
and people would not want to marry with those with questionable parentage.
So we are already, as I said, touching on what will be
major themes of מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamot. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, והיא
עמוקה משאול, ve-hi amuka mi-sheol, it's like deeper than even like the
depths, the netherworld. שנאמר, shene'emar, meaning because it's worse than being in
the netherworld. Being in הרפניא Harfanya is worse worse than being in
גיהנום. Gehinnom. שנאמר, shene'emar, because the verse says: מיד שאול אפדם ממות
אגאלם, mi-yad sheol efdem mi-mavet eg-alem, I will redeem them from the
netherworld, from death I will redeem them. ואילו פסוליתא דהרפניא, Ve-ilu psuliso
de-Harfanya, fine, somebody who's in the netherworld could be saved and redeemed,
but their invalidity if they their ממזרות, mamzerut לית ליה תקנתא, leit
lei takanta, you can't fix being a ממזר. Okay, so again now
we're going from just a question of questionable parentage to a real
ממזרות mamzerut type of a concern. So it's really like a disastrous
state to be in. So פסולי דהרפניא psulei d'Harfanya משום פסולי דמישנג.
mishum psulei d'Meshang. Now the גמרא Gemara says that the people who
were פסול pasul in הרפניא, Harfanya, they came from the people of
מישנג, Meshang, which was a place that was not as bad, like
but you know, some of the people there had questionable parentage and
they wound up going to הרפניא. Harfanya. And פסולי דמישנג, psulei d'Meshang,
and the people from מישנג, Meshang, משום פסולי דתרמוד, mishum psulei d'Tarmod,
were came from so, you know, came from the פסול pasul people
in תרמוד, Tarmod, which we had been discussing before. And פסולי דתרמוד
משום עבדי שלמה, psulei d'Tarmod mishum avdei Shlomo, and they came from
the slaves of שלמה Shlomo that had intermarried with the Jewish women.
והיינו דאמרי אינשי, vehaynu d'amri inshi, and that's what people say, כבא
רבה וכבא זוטא, kava raba vekava zuta, מינדא ואזלא, minda ve'azla, a
big measuring box and a small measuring box, it rolls and it
goes לשאול lish'ol to שאול. Sheol. ומשאול לתרמוד umish'ol leTarmod and from
שאול Sheol to תרמוד Tarmod because all these places שאול Sheol is,
as we said, on a higher level, there's redemption from שאול. Sheol.
All the places of questionable heritage and ממזרות mamzerut, are lower than
שאול Sheol in this image, you know, visually lower. So it goes
to שאול Sheol and from שאול Sheol to תרמוד Tarmod and from
תרמוד Tarmod to מישנג Meshang and from מישנג Meshang to הרפניא. Harfanya.
So everything like rolls downhill. So all the פסולים psulim roll downhill
and you get further and further and less and less able to
be redeemed. So it's a very sort of a depressing type of
an image, you know, but in a way I hope that one
can hear a little bit of a subtext of a little sense
of like, you know, of poignancy or of sympathy, like what it
means to be there and to have no solution, you know, and
that is a thing. Obviously חז״ל Chazal were very interested in trying
to work, you know, with the issue of ממזרות mamzerut. and find
solutions to it and ספק ממזרים מותר safek mamzerim mutar and all
those things, but that didn't change the fact that there was still
this heightened concern of יחוס yichus and that somebody who really was
פגם יוחסין pegam yuchsin was in a way very much rejected and
went to a different city and was completely cut off and nobody
wanted to marry with them. So חז״ל Chazal were trying to temper
that somewhat, but that doesn't change those harsh realities.
So anyway, so what we have now had in this last עמוד
amud is a real distillation of a lot of things we'll be
seeing. Number one, issues of ממזרות, mamzerut heightened concerns of יחוס, yichus,
do we know who we're marrying with, etc. in different places. Who
are people in different places? That's a big concern that we'll get
to, to identify the nature of people from this place and that
place and so on. And this whole issue of Jewish identity. Again,
the idea of one opinion that one Jewish parent creates a ממזר,
a Jew who's a ממזר, whether it's the Jewish mother or Jewish
father, quite shocking in both directions. And the other where the גמרא
Gemara is asserting what we take for granted, which is the idea
of matrilineal descent and not an issue of ממזרות. Either you're Jewish
or you're not Jewish, but not a ממזרות issue. Okay, so at
some way to end this פרק, perek, הדרן עלך חמישה עשר נשים,
hadran alach chamisha asar nashim, let us try to start getting some
headway into the next פרק. perek. כיצד אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו?
keitzad eshet achiv shelo haya be'olamo?
What's the scenario of, going back to that early משנה? mishna? Remember
we had the case of one of the people that there's an
ערווה erva is your brother's wife when the brother wasn't around, right?
And brother's wife is normally the מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, but
if the brother was born afterwards, after then there is no מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibbum after the brother died. Like, if שמעון Shimon
is born after, let's say ראובן שמעון ולוי. Reuven Shimon veLevi. Okay,
so ראובן Reuven marries a woman רחל. Rachel. לוי Levi isn't born
yet. ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are around. ראובן Reuven marries רחל.
Rachel. ראובן Reuven dies and then לוי Levi is born. Okay, so
in that case לוי Levi has no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum
with רחל Rachel because he wasn't alive at the same time ראובן
Reuven was. And therefore רחל Rachel to him is just brother's wife
and is an ערווה. erva. And now if רחל Rachel marries שמעון,
Shimon, שמעון Shimon does יבום yibbum with רחל. Rachel. Okay, so in
that case and then שמעון Shimon dies, so then רחל Rachel is
ערווה erva and that's the case of צרת ערווה. tzarat erva.
Right? Is that clear? Should I do that again? Hope people have
that.
ראובן Reuven marries רחל. Rachel. Okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are
alive. Just have to get rid of this one. ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon are alive. Okay, ראובן Reuven marries רחל. Rachel. Okay, and
then ראובן Reuven dies. That's what happens number one. Then at stage
number two לוי Levi is born. Okay, so at this stage this
is אשת אח eshet ach because there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
yibbum. Okay, so she's an ערווה. erva. Now שמעון Shimon here is
married to שרה, Sarah, we'll keep similar first letters. Okay, so שמעון
Shimon now does יבום yibbum with
רחל. Rachel. Okay, that's stage number three. Okay, so now he's got
these two wives. And then stage number four is, we'll use red,
stage number four is שמעון Shimon dies. Okay,
so now לוי, Levi, what's לוי'ס... Levi's... relationship to רחל? Rachel? ערבה,
Erva, אשת אח שלא היה בעולמו. Eshet Ach Shelo Haya Beolamo.
So what's שרה's Sarah status? צרת ערבה. Tzarat Erva. So that's the
משנה Mishna of צרת ערבה Tzarat Erva by אשת אח שלא היה
בעולמו. Eshet Ach Shelo Haya Beolamo. All right, so let's take a
look.
כיצד אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, Keitzad Eshet Achiv Shelo Haya Beolamo,
שני אחים, Shnei Achim, ראובן ושמעון, Reuven VeShimon, ומת אחד מהם, u'met
echad mehem, ראובן Reuven died. ונולד להם אח, Ve'nolad lahem ach, and
then לוי Levi is born. אחר כך יבם השני את אשת אחיו,
Achar kach yibem hasheni et eshet achiv, and then שמעון Shimon does
יבום Yibbum with רחל. Rachel. ומת, U'met, and then שמעון Shimon died.
הראשונה, Ha'rishona, the first one, רחל, Rachel, יוצא משום אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו, yotzei mishum eshet achiv shelo haya be'olamo, is an ערבה
Erva to לוי. Levi. והשנייה, Ve'ha'shniya, and שרה, Sarah, משום צרתה, mishum
tzarata, is צרת ערבה. Tzarat Erva. Now עשה בה מאמר asah bah
maamar ומת, u'met, so let's say שמעון Shimon did not do יבום.
Yibbum. But let's say he was planning on doing יבום Yibbum but
he did מאמר, maamar, which is like a קידושין, a Rabbinic קידושין
when יבום Yibbum is intended. So in that type of a case,
right, and then he died. Now is רחל Rachel actually דאורייתא? de'oraisa?
Is רחל, Rachel, you know, it's like an ערבה Erva under the
יבום Yibbum context? דאורייתא, de'oraisa, רחל Rachel is not part of the
יבום Yibbum with שמעון. Shimon. שמעון Shimon דאורייתא de'oraisa was only married
to שרה Sarah and the יבום Yibbum is only with שרה. Sarah.
רחל Rachel is really irrelevant because this did not really make them
married biblically. But since Rabbinically they're married, so רחל Rachel is now
a sort of ערבה יבום Erva Yibbum because she's quasi יבום Yibbum
because of שמעון's Shimon quasi marriage to her. So, so, so שרה
Sarah is like a quasi צרת ערבה. Tzarat Erva. The problem is
you can't walk away from that situation because
biblically רחל's Rachel out of the picture and you really have a
מצווה mitzvah with שרה. Sarah. So we're not going to let him
do יבום Yibbum because it's sort of like ערבה Erva and צרת
ערבה, Tzarat Erva, but we're not going to let him walk away,
so he's going to have to do חליצה chalitza to שרה Sarah
because that's where his real obligation is. So let's just read that.
עשה בה מאמר, Asah bah maamar, if שמעון Shimon did a מאמר
maamar with רחל, Rachel, ומת, u'met, and then he died, שנייה, shniya,
the second one meaning
שרה, Sarah, חולצת ולא מתייבמת. choletzet ve'lo mityabemet. He has to do
חליצה chalitza because he has a real obligation of יבום Yibbum to
שרה Sarah because רחל Rachel is really not in the picture, but
he cannot do יבום Yibbum because it sort of looks like a
case of צרת ערבה. Tzarat Erva. Yes.
Wouldn't it be the case even if you didn't do מאמר maamar
because of the זיקה? zika?
זיקה. Zika. So that's a good question and we'll get to the
זיקה zika issue.
But no, it wouldn't. Because because that's a זיקה zika that's still
going back to I don't think the זיקה zika there, you're right,
sometimes we make a זיקה zika quasi קידושין but not in this
case. But we'll hopefully we'll get back to that. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, מאן
דתני ראשונה לא משתבש. man de'tani rishona lo mishtabesh. So if some
say ראשונה rishona comes to describe רחל. Rachel. So there were some
that had the גרסה girsa the first one, meaning רחל, Rachel, and
they refer to her as ראשונה. rishona. That's not a problem. מאן
דתני שנייה לא משתבש. Man de'tani shniya lo mishtabesh. Some describe רחל
Rachel in this scenario as שנייה, shniya, which sounds wrong. What does
it mean second? She was the first one in the picture. So
let's take a look. But he says that would not be a
wrong text. מאן דתני ראשונה לא משתבש, Man de'tani rishona lo mishtabesh,
if you said ראשונה rishona that's not an error. Top of יז
עמוד ב. Yud Zayin Amud Beis. מאי ראשונה? Mai rishona? ראשונה לנפילה.
Rishona l'nefilla. It meant that שרה Sarah was the first one that
you started doing יבום Yibbum with. ראובן Reuven died—I mean, I keep
deciding שרה—רחל. So רחל Rachel. here is referred to the first one.
I said לוי Levi for the first one is an ערבה Erva
and the second one שרה Sarah is a צרת ערבה. Tzarat Erva.
So it's referring to רחל Rachel here, it works good because it's
always with the ר's, reishes, it's referring to רחל Rachel as ראשונה.
rishona. Oh look, and שרה Sarah is שנייה. shniya. Okay, very nice.
So that's our משנה, Mishna, okay, ראשונה rishona because she's the first
one of the whole mix. So and it says for the ראשונה
rishona she's an ערבה Erva and for the שנייה shniya is צרת
ערבה. Tzarat Erva. So מאי ראשונה? mai rishona? ראשונה לנפילה. rishona l'nefilla.
רחל Rachel is the first one that started doing יבום Yibbum when
ראובן Reuven died, she was already in the process of יבום. Yibbum.
So she's the first one we even discussed through this whole process.
ומאן דתני שנייה, U'man de'tani shniya, but if you refer to רחל
Rachel as the second wife, what does it mean second? לא משתבש,
lo mishtabesh, that's not an error.
מאי שנייה? Mai shniya? שנייה בנישואין. Shniya b'nisuim. Which is a very
funny read. So שנייה shniya does not mean second, שנייה shniya means
the one that's been married twice. So those that had refer to
רחל Rachel where it says when שמעון Shimon died, רחל Rachel is
an ערבה Erva to לוי Levi and referred to as second, what
it mean second, why is רחל Rachel second? It means the woman
who's been married twice. Okay as opposed to שרה Sarah who's the
woman who's only been married once. Again that's not exactly what the
word שנייה shniya means, but okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, שנייה בנישואין. shniya b'nisuim. Fine,
that's the end of that. That wasn't so interesting. Let's get, let's
get at least a little bit in terms of the דרשות *drashot*.
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו *eshet achiv shelo haya be'olamo*, היכא כתיבא
*heicha ketiva*? Where does it say this idea that if the brother
wasn't alive at the same time there's no מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום
yibum *yibum* and therefore it's an ערווה *ervah*? So אמר רב יהודה
אמר קרא *amar Rav Yehuda amar kra*, אמר קרא *amar kra*, the
verse says: כי ישבו אחים achim יחדיו *ki yeshvu achim yachdav*, if
brothers sit together, שהייתה להם ישיבה אחת בעולם *shehayta lahem yeshiva achat
be'olam*, they were living together at the same time. פרט לאשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו *prat le'eshet achiv shelo haya be'olamo*, if you're born
after the brother dies, then there's no מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום yibum
*yibum*. That's the word יחדיו *yachdav*. Okay, and that's the, that's the
דרשה *drasha*. Now that we're looking at the פסוק *pasuk*, we're going
to say other things we learn from that פסוק *pasuk*. יחדיו *yachdav*
means מיוחדים בנחלה *meyuchadim benachala*, that they have to be, have a
similar inheritance. פרט לאחיו מן האם *prat le'achiv min ha'em*. Here's we
learn another very important principle. It's only paternal brother, not maternal. Because
a person inherits through the father. So if you have a brother,
a paternal brother, then you'll inherit from one another. But not, but
if you have a maternal brother, you won't inherit. So the word
יחדיו *yachdav* is also teaching us that they have to be paternal
brothers. רבה אמר *Rabba amar*, אחים מן האב יליף אח ואח מבני
יעקב Yaakov *achim min ha'av yalif ach ve'ach mibnei Yaakov*. No, we
learn that idea of paternal brothers from יעקב *Yaakov*'s sons. Right, because
they say to יוסף *Yosef*, שנים עשר אחים אנחנו *shneim asar achim
anachnu*. And here it says כי ישבו אחים יחדיו *ki yeshvu achim
yachdav*. So the sons of יעקב *Yaakov* are only brothers, they're only
paternal brothers. So that's not maternal. So from there we learn the
idea of brother means paternal. מה להלן מן האב ולא מן האם
אף כאן מן האב ולא מן האם *ma lehalan min ha'av velo
min ha'em af kan min ha'av velo min ha'em*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, ולילף אח ואח מהעריות *velilyaf ach ve'ach meha'arayot*. Why
don't we learn where it says אחיך *achicha* like אשת אחיך *eshet
achicha* by the עריות arayos. *arayot*? And we learn later that that
means even, even maternal brother. So maybe here too the מצוה *mitzvah*
of יבום yibum *yibum* is even maternal brother. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, no. דנין אחים מאחים ואין דנין אחים מאחיך *danin achim
me'achim ve'ein danin achim me'achicha*. No, we'd rather learn כי ישבו אחים
*ki yeshvu achim* from by the case of יעקב *Yaakov*'s children where
it says שנים עשר אחים אנחנו *shneim asar achim anachnu* and not
from the עריות *arayot* where it refers to it as אחיך *achicha*.
It's not the exact same word. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
מאי נפקא מינה *mai nafka mina*? What do I care? אחים *achim*
or אחיך *achicha*, it's close enough. הא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *ha
tana devei Rabbi Yishmael*. רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* teaches in the case
by צרעת *tzara'at*. One פסוק *pasuk* says ושב הכהן *veshav hakohen*, the
כהן *kohen* returns. Another פסוק *pasuk* says ובא הכהן *uva hakohen*, the
כהן *kohen* comes. And even though they're different words, essentially it's referring
to the same thing. זו היא שיבה זו היא ביאה *zo hi
shiva zo hi via*. That we can link those two פסוקים *psukim*
because essentially it's the same act even though it's different words. So
why not learn אחים *achim* from אחיך *achicha*? So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, no. הני מילי היכא דליכא דדמי ליה *hani mili heicha delika
demidi dedami lei*. That's when there's nothing that's a closer match. אבל
היכא דאיכא דדמי ליה *aval heicha de'ika demidi dedami lei*, if there's
a closer match, we could learn אחים *achim* from אחים *achim* or
we could learn אחים *achim* from אחיך *achicha*. So in that case
מידי דדמי ליה ילפינן *midi dedami lei yalpinan*. We learn it from
the closer match. So the word אחים *achim* is learned from יעקב
*Yaakov*'s sons which are all paternal brothers, not from the עריות *arayot*
which is even a maternal brother. Let's just read a little bit
more, we're like a minute over, but let's just read a little
bit more. ולילף אח ואח מלוט *velilyaf ach ve'ach miLot*? Why not
learn it from לוט *Lot*? דכתיב כי אנשים אחים אנחנו *dechtiv ki
anashim achim anachnu*. And there אחים *achim* means even like a nephew,
not even a brother. So maybe that's what the פסוק *pasuk* is
saying. ומסתברא מבני יעקב הוה ליה למילף משום דמופני *umistabra mibnei Yaakov
hava lei lemilaf mishum demufni*. The word by יעקב *Yaakov* of אחים
*achim* is an extra word. מכדי דהוה ליה למכתב *michdi dehavah lei
lemichtav*, it could have said שנים עשר עבדיך בני אבינו *shneim asar
avadecha bnei avinu*. Why did it have to say the word brothers?
It could have said we're all descendant of our father. דכתיב אחים
*dechtiv achim*, שמע מינה לאפנויי *shma mina le'afnuyei*. That's to make it
an extra word so to tell you you learn from there paternal
brothers and not from לוט *Lot* where it more means relative or
nephew. Okay, I should say about the גמרא *Gemara*'s possibility that it
means nephew. It seems a little absurd to us. But, I forget
who it was, whether it was the Samaritans or others, again, the
whole problem of how do you do יבום yibum *yibum* if it's
an איסור ערווה *issur ervah*? So the one, one of the non-rabbinic
sects said that the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum* is only by
a relative who's not a brother. By like a case of nephew.
And they said the word אחים *achim* is לאו דווקא *lav davka*.
אחים *achim* means like by לוט *Lot*, it means relative but not
brother. And that the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum* only applies where
there's no איסור ערווה *issur ervah*. So the fact that the גמרא
*Gemara* is suggesting it to us maybe seems absurd, but you should
actually be aware there were people in the period of בית שני
*Bayit Sheni* that דווקא *davka* interpreted it that way. So let's just
read one more line. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ואצטריך למכתב אחים
ואצטריך למכתב יחדיו *ve'itztreich lemichtav achim ve'itztreich lemichtav yachdav*. It had to
say both. דאי כתב רחמנא אחים *de'i katav Rachmana achim*, if it
just said brothers, הוה אמינא hava amina נילף אח ואח מלוט *hava
amina lilyaf ach ve'ach miLot*, we'd learn it from לוט *Lot*. וכי
תימא לא מופני *vechi teima lo mofni*, and you'll say oh the
word by לוט *Lot* isn't extra? No, הא איהו נמי מופני *ha
ihu nami mofni*, it is extra. מכדי דהוה ליה למכתב ריעים *michdi
dehavah lei lemichtav rei'im*, it could have said to אברהם *Avraham* we're
friends. דכתיב אחים *dechtiv achim*, of course there was a different point.
Anyway שמע מינה לאפנויי *shma mina le'afnuyei*. Fine. So we're rejecting what
we said before, you could have learned from לוט *Lot*. So אחים
*achim* itself would have not told you only brothers. כתב רחמנא יחדיו
*katav Rachmana yachdav*. That's why it says יחדיו *yachdav*. המיוחדים בנחלה *hameuchadim
benachala*. You're in the same inheritance level. Brothers inherit together from their
father. So יחדיו *yachdav* tells us that אחים *achim* means brothers and
not other relatives. ואי כתב רחמנא יחדיו *ve'i katav Rachmana yachdav*... הוה
אמינא דמיחדי באבא ובימא. Maybe they share a mother and a father.
So צריכא, tzricha, so it has to say אחים to tell me
no, just like יעקב paternal brothers is enough. I say והא מהיכא
תיתי, veha meheicha teisi, why would I have thought that you need
to share both a mother and a father? יבום בנחלה תלה רחמנא.
yibum banachala tala Rachmana. יבום is about inheritance. Now that's a fascinating
statement. We said יבום is about יקום על שם אחיו המת, yakum
al shem achiv hamet,
but the גמרא understands that part of that idea of, you know,
following in the brother's name is about taking over the brother's inheritance
and being the one like to, you know, the brother-in-law gets the
נחלה nachala and passes it on to the child. So that's a
fascinating assumption the גמרא has that יבום is about inheritance. And the
first time we're seeing that. ונחלה מאב, venachala me'av, and that's the
father. So of course the maternal relationship doesn't matter. ולא מאם. velo
me'em. גמרא says no, אצטריך, itztrich, I still might have not needed
it. סלקא דעתך אמינא הוה חידוש הוא דקא משתרי ערוה גביה. salaka
deitach amina havei chiddush hu deka mishtarei erva gabei. The whole thing
is a חידוש, chiddush, right? That we're allowing עריות. So אימא, eima,
so maybe I'll try to limit this חידוש chiddush as much as
possible. עד דמיחדי באבא ובימא, ad demeyachadei be'abba uve'imma, unless it's the
closest relationship possible, that we'll allow. It's so ironic. As opposed to
say nephew, let's solve the problem by making it a more distant
relationship, I might have thought that we'll allow it, it does override
but only in the closest relationship.
So צריכא, tzricha, so therefore you needed it. So the end of
the idea we learned, the idea that you have to be alive
at the same time, and you go by paternal brothers, you don't
need to share a mother, and the fascinating הוה אמינא number one
that it might have been talking about a nephew, which is an
interesting solution to the problem, and number two, the idea that יבום
is about נחלה, nachala, which is also a fascinating assumption. Let's pick
up at this משנה. mishna.